We hit the jackpot during our data mining expedition
but the gold we found was not without impurities
The accuracy of our data
relies heavily on how well we refine it.
The more we clean and polish our data,
the greater the level of accuracy we can achieve.
And with that, we step into our data cleaning operation.
The impurities in the data include:
Familiar data being Alien
Data that violated regulations
Islandic data
Conflicting data
And Threatening scope creep
To kick things off,
we have our first hurdle
Familiar data being Alien.
Let's delve into the data we've extracted
By honing in on these two tables.
we'll discover they both have a country column in common.
Upon closer examination,
the countries that should be well-known in both tables seem strangely unfamiliar.
But how is this possible?
It turns out that one country is referred to by a completely different name in the other table.
To swiftly resolve the issue at hand,
we utilized Excel's vlookup function.
By designating one table as the standard,
the other table was examined for any matches.
Any countries that did not have a match were manually edited to align with the country names in the standard table.
A quick re-run of the function would confirm if the cleaning process was complete.
In our ongoing data examination,
we uncovered a criminal data impurity.
According to the regulations of Data normalization,
subsection first normal form,
a table ought to contain attributes or columns with atomic values.
In simple terms,
one value per cell,
not two not three,
just one.
Our main contents table breached this regulation.
The resolution for this offense involved employing Python code to split the multi-value cells into separate single-value cells.
At present, our raw data is entirely isolated,
requiring us to devise a solution for establishing a connection between the tables.
Without a means of linking the life expectancy and main contents table,
it becomes impossible to ascertain whether individuals from countries with white meat-based dishes
enjoy a longer life expectancy than those from countries with red meat-based dishes.
The solution closely resembles the one we previously discussed.
By leveraging Excel's VLOOKUP function,
we can seamlessly incorporate ID columns into other tables by referring to a reference table.
Although this method is highly effective for smaller datasets,
it's recommended to explore alternative solutions for larger datasets to ensure efficient processing.
Demonstrating the solution using the “main contents” table;
we start by copying the unique values of the national dish column to a new table called Dishes.
We then create an ID column in the dishes table and assign an ID value to each national dish.
Setting the dishes table as the reference table,
we add the ID values to the main contents table.
The updated table bears this appearance.
It is now safe to drop the National Dish column as the ID column is sufficient.
Tailoring the solution to each table,
we not only get data that can now be linked but can also communicate a universal message.
The last pair of impurities we stumbled upon were intimately
intertwined, originating from a shared source.
Throughout our data mining expedition,
we amassed data from many websites.
Two of which housed the numerous countries with their respective national cuisines.
These two houses were at loggerheads and their data was laced with the last two impurities.
In a nutshell,
the data sourced from website 1 stands out as the primary offender.
Both datasets 1 and 2 include countries that overlap.
However, , it's quite intriguing to observe that certain nations in Dataset 1 have dissimilar national dishes listed in comparison to Dataset 2.
To prevent the project from going down a rabbit hole,
only one dish was allowed to be designated as the national dish.
Dataset 1 breached this scope, resulting in certain countries having more than one dish listed as their national dish.
To cleanse out both of these impurities,
Dataset 2 was chosen as the authoritative dataset, incorporating only the countries from Dataset 1 that were absent in Dataset 2.
For the countries from Dataset 1 that were missing in Dataset 2
and brought along the burden of scope creep,
a meticulous process of manual trimming was carried out.
This involved replacing the multiple dishes with a single dish carefully selected through thorough research and human judgment.
Now that we've wrapped up the cleaning process and eliminated all impurities from our data,
it is vital to secure an appropriate storage solution.
This is crucial to avoid any additional contamination that could jeopardize the precision of our analysis.
And thus, we move forward to the next phase: the data modelling operation.
We are grateful for the time you have invested in this endeavour.
If you need access to the code used for the data cleaning process,
please consult the Jupyter notebooks provided below.
Thank You!